<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach't at a publick ordination in a country congregation, on Acts XIII. 2, 3. Together with an exhortation to the minister and people, / by another brother.</title>
            <author>Offley, William, 1659 or 60-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O159C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19633</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12172492</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12172492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90119)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 876:2 or 2625:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach't at a publick ordination in a country congregation, on Acts XIII. 2, 3. Together with an exhortation to the minister and people, / by another brother.</title>
                  <author>Offley, William, 1659 or 60-1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrance, at the Angel in the Poultry.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Offley by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel position 876:22 identified as Wing S2630 (entry cancelled).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XIII, 2-3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach't at a Publick Ordination IN A <hi>Country Congregation,</hi> ON <hi>ACTS</hi> XIII. 2, 3.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER <hi>With an Exhortation to the Minister and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> By another Brother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Lawrance,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:172319:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172319:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THAT this plain, homeſpun Diſcourſe, wherein there is little but what is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and common, ſhould he preſſed, not to Death, but to Life and Light, in this Critical Learned Age, wherein there is ſo much Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement made in ſeveral Points of Natural Knowledge (I wiſh there were an anſwerable Improvement in point of Morality) is to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed more to the Favour of its Judges, than either its own Deſert, or the Inclination of the Author; for it is not agreeable to his Humour, to have the World troubled with old Matter new vamp'd up, and put into a new Dreſs; (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it may be in ſuch Practical Points as may have a powerful Influence upon the Affections, which ſtand in continual need of Excitation) only he would not be guilty of ſo much Stiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſuch an over-weening Conceit of his own
<pb facs="tcp:172319:3"/>Judgment, as to reſiſt the Joynt-deſires of his Brethren: And ſince they were the Inſtigators to, and Promoters of this Publication, he expects that they ſhould be reſponſible for thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it may be chargeable withal.</p>
            <p>I know nothing that can be pleaded in its behalf, but that things are laid pretty cloſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: Nor have I ſeen any Sermon printed of late upon this Subject; ſo that poſſibly it may be new to many, and conſequently the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.</p>
            <p>If it may conduce to Edification, either in point of Knowledge or Practiſe, that will be an abundant Recompence for the no great Pains it coſt the Author, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Devoted to the Service of thy Faith.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172319:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS XIII. 2, 3.</bibl> As they miniſtred to the Lord and faſted,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Sept.</hi> 16-96.</note> the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate we Barnabas and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them. And when they had faſted and pray'd, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away.</q>
            </head>
            <p>THIS Book of the <hi>Acts,</hi> is an Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory of the Primitive Church, from Chriſt's Aſcention to the ſecond Year of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment at <hi>Rome,</hi> which is about twenty ſeven Years in all.</p>
            <p>It gives an account now the Chriſtian Church was firſt planted and water'd, was firſt: gather'd and propagated both among Jews and Gentiles. Among the Jews, chiefly by <hi>Peter</hi>'s Miniſtry (whoſe Apoſtle he was, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.8.) This is in the twelve firſt Chapters of the Book: And alſo among the Gentiles, by the Miniſtry of <hi>Paul</hi> (who was their Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.13.) from the beginning of this Chapter to the end of the Book. So that here begins the Hiſtory of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Miniſtry to the Gentiles; and it begins with his <hi>Separation</hi> and <hi>Ordination</hi> for this work, in the words of my Text, which I ſhall open particularly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As they miniſtred to the Lord.]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I ſhall not loſe time in confuting the Popiſh Dream concerning the Sence of this word, as if it ſignified <hi>Sacrificing,</hi> or <hi>ſaying of Maſs;</hi> as thoſe two great Cardinals <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> tranſlate it; the latter of which ſaith, <hi>Whenſoever it is applied to the Sacred Miniſtry and uſed abſolutely, it is always taken for the Act of Sacrificing,</hi> De Miſſa. l. 1. c. 13. But this Conceit is ſufficiently confuted by the Learned <hi>Caſaubon</hi> in his Exercitations againſt <hi>Baronius, Exerc.</hi> 16. c. 41.</p>
            <p>It ſignifies generally, all manner of Publick Service, whether Sacred or Civil, and is applied to Angelical Service, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>miniſtring Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it muſt ſignifie all Religious Exerciſes of the publick Worſhip of God, by Praying, Preaching, Singing, and the like, being joyn'd with <hi>[to the Lord]</hi> and <hi>[faſted.]</hi> Hence <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> expounds it by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Preaching,</hi> and the Syriack by <hi>Praying.</hi> Where obſerve,</p>
            <p>That the Holy Ghoſt takes this occaſion, when they were met together in God's preſence about his Work, to reveal himſelf to them, and give them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Inſtructions and Directions concerning his Will, and their Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And faſted.]</hi> Probably this Faſt was undertaken by the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> in behalf of their Mother-Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which at this time was under great Perſecution by <hi>Herod,</hi> as may be ſeen in the former Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſaid.]</hi> viz. By an inward Inſtinct or Motion to theſe Prophets here mentioned, <hi>v.</hi> 1. God the Father ſpake outwardly by his Son Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1. Here he ſpeaks inwardly by the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo he does ſt ill in ſome degree.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172319:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Do ye.]</hi> (ſo 'tis in the Original) Who were theſe <hi>[ye?]</hi> The Prophets and Teachers whoſe names are expreſs'd, <hi>v.</hi> 1. The Command is given to them; they are the Perſons imploy'd by the Holy Ghoſt for this Work, and in this Affair.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Separate me.]</hi> This ſome take to be an Anſwer to their Prayers for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Church, then under Perſecution; as if the Holy Ghoſt had ſaid, I have heard your Prayers, the Church ſhall be preſerved; and as a Teſtimony thereof, <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> ſhall be now ſent forth to enlarge its Tents, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate its Doctrine, and to beget many Sons and Daughters to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barnabas and Saul.]</hi> Here now ariſes a great Difficulty: If <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> were Apoſtles before, What means this new Ordination? They were ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated to the Work of the Miniſtry before, What need it be done again?</p>
            <p>To make way for the reſolving this Doubt, and removing this Difficulty, I ſhall lay before you, what things are certain by Scripture in this caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) It is certain, that <hi>Paul</hi> was called to be an Apoſtle immediately by Chriſt, for he affirms this of himſelf, That as he did not receive his Apoſtleſhip <hi>from Man,</hi> ſo neither <hi>by Man, but by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1.1. <hi>viz.</hi> at Chriſt's appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him in his Journy to <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> for then he tells him, <hi>I have appeared unto thee for this purpoſe, to <hi>make the a Miniſter, and a Witneſs,</hi>
               </hi> (Mark that) —<hi>delivering thee from the People, and from the Gentiles, unto whom <hi>now I ſend thee.</hi>
               </hi> Sure this was plainly his Call to the Apoſtleſhip. And therefore he ſeems to date his Birth as an Apoſtle, or the beginning of his Apoſtleſhip from that time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Laſt of all he was ſeen of me alſo, as of one born out of due time.</hi> Mark it, There was the Time of his <hi>Birth,</hi> viz. as an Apoſtle Then he had his general Commiſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Immediately after this Call, <hi>Paul</hi> ſets upon the work of Preaching, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.20. <hi>Strait way he preached Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3) Both <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> were Members of the Presbytery, or Bench of Church-Officers at <hi>Antioch,</hi> for they are reckon'd among the Prophets and Teachers there, <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="4">(4) Before this, <hi>Barnabas</hi> was ſent by the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to confirm the Diſciples at <hi>Antioch,</hi> who, together with <hi>Saul,</hi> preach'd to them a whole Year, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.22-26.</p>
            <p n="5">(5) After this, and never before, <hi>Barnabas</hi> is called an Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.14. <hi>which when the Apoſtles Barnabus and Saul heard of</hi>—</p>
            <p n="6">(6) This <hi>Separation</hi> was performed with the ſolemn Rites of Ordination, <hi>viz.</hi> Faſting, Prayer, and Impoſition of hands.</p>
            <p>What then ſhall we ſay was the End and Deſign of it? Will you give me leave to offer my Conjecture about it? What if we ſhould ſay, That tho' <hi>Paul</hi> was called to be an Apoſtle before this, immediately by Chriſt, Chap. 9. yet he was never ordain'd and ſet apart by the Officers of the Church till now? For tho' immediately after Chriſt's appearing to him, <hi>Ananias</hi> was ſent to lay hands
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172319:4"/>on him, yet that was only to reſtore him to his ſight, as the words plainly ſhew, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.12. <hi>He hath ſeen in a Viſion a Man coming in, and putting his hand on him, that he might receive his ſight.</hi> So that he had before no ſetting apart by Impoſition of hands, that we read of.</p>
            <p>Then for <hi>Barnabas,</hi> tho' he was imploy'd in the Work of the Miniſtry before, yet we read not elſewhere of any Ordination he had; and it is not till after this that he is called an Apoſtle, as I obſerv'd afore: So that this ſeems to be his Admiſſion into, and Ordination for that Office. This I humbly propoſe to Conſideration; But I grant that the more received Opinion is, That they were ordain'd before, and that this Separation was to give them a more expreſs and particular Miſſion to the Gentiles. They were called to the general Office and Work of the Miniſtry and Apoſtleſhip before, this now is a ſetting them apart more peculiarly for this branch of the Work. Therefore ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the Work</hi> (not Office) <hi>whereto I have called them.</hi> The <hi>Office</hi> is one thing, the <hi>Work</hi> of the Office is another. <q>Called they were before, and deſigned by God to be Preachers to the Gentiles, and now they were publickly inaugurated to that great and eminent Service. <bibl>
                     <hi>Jus Div. Min. Evang.</hi> p. 148.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, Suppoſing that this was the end of their Separation, from this Example of Ordination upon ſuch a ſpecial occaſion, I think I may fairly infer,</p>
            <p>That repeating of Impoſition of hands upon an extraordinary occaſion, ſo it be done by way of Accumulation, and further Confirmation of what went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and not by way of Derogation, Denial, or Renouncing the former Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as invalid, may be admitted without any Irregularity, or breach of Goſpel-order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Work.]</hi> Tho' the Office of the Miniſtry be an honourable Office, yet withal it is a laborious Office: A <hi>Work,</hi> not a Play. 'Tis that that requires <hi>Attendance,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Paul</hi> calls upon <hi>Timothy</hi> to be <hi>inſtant</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which properly ſignifies ſtanding to, or over a buſineſs; and imports Earneſtneſs and Diligence, and that at all times, both <hi>in ſeaſon,</hi> and <hi>out of ſeaſon,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. and therefore requires a Man's preſence with his Flock or Charge, and cannot be performed by a Curate or Deputy, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.8.</p>
            <p>This Work here, was to preach the Goſpel to the Gentiles, as was ſaid: Now this was a great Work, and not to be undertaken without a ſpecial Call from God; which therefore <hi>Peter</hi> had for one particular occaſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. and theſe two Apoſtles had for a more general purpoſe. This, I ſay, was a great Work. See after what a lofty rate <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of this Myſtery of Chriſt, as he calls it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.5-9. <hi>By Revelation he made known unto me the Myſtery, which in other Ages was not made known unto the Sons of Men, as it is now revealed to his holy Apoſtles and Prophets by the Spirit, that the Gentiles ſhould be fellow-heirs, and of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel, whereof I was made a Miniſter according to the Gift of the Grace of God, given unto me by the effectual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172319:5"/>working of his power: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto me, who am the leaſt of all Saints is this grace given, that I ſhould Preach among the Gentiles the unſearchable riches of Chriſt, and to make all Men ſee what is the fellowſhip of the myſtery which from the beginning of the world has been hid in God who created all things by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— <hi>Whereto I have called them.</hi>] Theſe words prove both the Deity and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonality of the Holy Ghoſt. He who calls Miniſters, and unto whoſe Service they are ſeparated <hi>ſeparate to me</hi>) is both God, and a diſtinct Perſon in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
            <p>— <hi>When they faſted and Pray'd.</hi>] All Works of Weight and Moment ought to be ſo undertaken. We ſhould not ſet upon 'em raſhly, or preſumptuouſly, truſting to our own ſtrength, but imploring God's Aſſiſtance and Bleſſing therein.</p>
            <p>— <hi>They laid their hands on 'em.</hi>] Of this I ſhall ſpeak anon.</p>
            <p>— <hi>They ſent 'em away.</hi>] There being Teachers enow at <hi>Antioch</hi> beſide, they might well be ſpared there, and go, the Holy Ghoſt cuts 'em out ſome other work: and the other Teachers did not let 'em lye trifling and loitering there, but immediately diſmiſt 'em with their Benediction, and ſent 'em about their Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>In the words thus open'd, obſerve two General Parts.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Command,</hi> and the <hi>Execution</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Command,</hi> obſerve,</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) The <hi>Time,</hi> when it was given; <hi>as they Miniſtred to the Lord, and Faſted.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(2.) The <hi>Perſon by whom</hi> it was given; <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſaid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(3.) The <hi>Perſons to whom</hi> it was given; to the Prophets and Teachers men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Ye.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(4.) The <hi>Matter</hi> of the Command; or Duty enjoyn'd; <hi>Separate me Barnabas and Saul.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(5.) The <hi>End</hi> of this <hi>Separation;</hi> or to what they were Separated; <hi>for the work whereto I have called them.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the <hi>Execution</hi> of this Command, here is both the <hi>Manner</hi> how they executed it; with <hi>Faſting, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Impoſition of hands:</hi> and the <hi>Conſequent</hi> thereof; <hi>they ſent them away.</hi> Hence obſerve.</p>
            <p>Doctr. <hi>It is the Inſtitution and Appointment of the Holy Ghoſt, that they that are Teaches, and Perſons in Office themſelves, ſhould ſeparate others for the work of the Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is directly to the buſineſs in hand, and fits the occaſion of our Meeting together at this time.</p>
            <p>In the handling of this I ſhall not ſpeak to every particular that may be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein, but ſingle out theſe Four Points, or Heads of Diſcourſe, as the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal to be inſiſted on.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The work of the Miniſtry is a ſeparate work.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>A Call from God, or the Holy Ghoſt, is not ſufficient to make a Man a Miniſter but he muſt be ſet apart by Church-Officers alſo.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172319:5"/>
               <item>3. <hi>Officers in the Church have Authority from Chriſt to ſet apart others.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>This muſt be done by Faſting, Prayer, and Impoſition of hands.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>The Work of a Miniſter is a ſeparate Work. Separate me,</hi> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt. Now Separation is <hi>From</hi> ſomething <hi>To</hi> ſomething: What they are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated <hi>To,</hi> is here expreſs'd; <hi>to the Work to which I have called them:</hi> But what they are ſeparated <hi>From,</hi> muſt be ſought for elſewhere.</p>
            <p>There is a general Separation common to all Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> from Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Unholineſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Come out from among them and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing.</hi> But that is not of this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for this Separation in the Text, is ſomething that is peculiar to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and that is (1) From all Lordly Dominion. (2) From all Civil, Secular Imployments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From all Lordly Dominion, and Secular Power and Authority. This is expreſly forbidden by Chriſt to his Miniſters. <hi>Matt.</hi> 20.25, 26. <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe Dominion over them,</hi> —<hi>but it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi> Here they are diſcharged from meddling with any Temporal Rule and Dominion; ſuch as they expected in Chriſt's Temporal Kingdom. So 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. —<hi>not being Lords over God's Heritage.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the ſame word that is uſed by <hi>Matthew.</hi> They muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Biſhoping it over the Lord's Flock,</hi> but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>Lording it over God's Heritage.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. It is the Obſervation of <hi>Beza</hi> upon the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in my Text, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>vel</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>nulla fit in Apoſtolieis ſcriptis mentio, cum de Eccleſiae politia diſſeritur; imo ne</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quidem; ut nullus ſe dominum ac principem cleri, ſed unius Principis ac Domini miniſtrum eſſe ſciat. In the Writings of the Apoſtles there is no mention made of Rulers, when the Government of the Church is ſpoken of, no nor ſo much as of Lords (or Maſters) that no one ſhould look upon himſelf as a Lord or Prince of God's Heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kingdom of Chriſt is not of this World, and therefore the Officers of his Kingdom muſt not exerciſe Worldly Power. As on the one hand we muſt not <hi>put aſunder what God has joyn'd together</hi> (Matt. 19.6.) ſo neither on the other hand muſt we joyn together what Chriſt has put aſunder. Indeed among the Heathen, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Power were united in the ſame Perſon. The Emperor <hi>Auguſtus</hi> aſſum'd that Power to himſelf, and afterwards all the Emperors took this Power upon them: Even <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and ſome of his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors continued it, tho' they were Chriſtians and hated Paganiſm, till at laſt the Emperor <hi>Gratian</hi> renounc'd it. And therefore the Pope, who pretending to be Chriſt's Vicar, is alſo a Temporal Monarch, is none of Chriſt's Officer but the Devil's: Not Chriſt but the Dragon gave him his Authority, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            <p>But yet it doth not follow from hence, That they have no Power at all. The very nature of an Office, includes ſomething of Power in it. What Officer has not Power and Authority to perform the Duties of his Office? Be he but a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172319:6"/>Overſeer of the Poor, Surveyor of the High-ways, ſome Power is annex'd peculiarly to his Office. So Miniſters, being Church-Officers, muſt have ſome Office-power belonging to them, which belongs not to others. True: They have no Civil, Secular, Worldly, Temporal Power over Mens Bodies or Eſtates, to puniſh them in their Perſons or Purſes; to Fine, Impriſon, or the like; but they have Spiritual Power: Spiritual (1) In reſpect of the <hi>Object,</hi> the Soul and Conſcience, or <hi>Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. (2) In reſpect of the <hi>Weapons</hi> they make uſe of in the exerciſe of this Power; not <hi>Carnal</hi> (and therefore Spiritual, and) <hi>mighty thro' God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. (3) In reſpect of the Ends of this Power; which are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Not by way of Dominion over the Peoples Faith (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.) nor for Deſtruction (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. &amp; 13.10.) <hi>viz.</hi> of the Spirit or Soul; but for the Deſtruction of the Fleſh (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.) for the demoliſhing the <hi>ſtrong-holds of Satan: caſting down imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and every high thing that exalts it ſelf againſt the Knowledge of God, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Captivity every thought to the Obedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. and on the contrary, for <hi>Edification,</hi> and building up in Faith and Holineſs (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8.) and for the Salvation of the Spirit or Soul, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</p>
            <p>This is all the Power that we claim.</p>
            <p>And this is that which Chriſt has confer'd upon us (and therefore cannot of right be denied unto us, or taken away from us.) A Power of <hi>Binding</hi> and <hi>Looſing;</hi> confer'd firſt upon <hi>Peter, Matt.</hi> 16.19. yet not upon him only (ſee <hi>Clark</hi>'s Annot. there) but upon the reſt alſo, c. 18.18. A Power of <hi>Remitting</hi> and <hi>Retaining Sins,</hi> John 20.23. This is the Power of the Keys, as Chriſt calls it there to <hi>Peter;</hi> which are diſtinguiſh'd into the Key of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and the Key of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Key of Doctrine;</hi> of Binding and Looſing; whereby is meant (in part at leaſt) (according to the ordinary uſe of that Phraſe among the Jews, as is ſhew'd at large in many Inſtances by Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> in <hi>Pool</hi>'s Latin Synopſis) teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is Lawful, and what Unlawful; declaring what is agreeable to the Word and Will of God, and what is contrary thereto. This is called by Chriſt <hi>the Key of Knowledge,</hi> Luke 11.52. <hi>i. e.</hi> The means whereby the Senſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is opened and made known to us; whereby we are let into the meaning of it, and ſee into it, as into a Room when the Door is open. Hereby a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter has Power to open and apply Scripture to the Souls of People, as occaſion requires; to apply Scripture Threatnings to the Impenitent, and Goſpel-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to Senſible Contrite Sinners. This is to uſe this Key for Binding and Looſing, according to this Senſe of that Phraſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There's the <hi>Key of Diſcipline;</hi> which is</p>
            <p n="1">(1) To Lock or Unlock, to ſhut or open the Church-doors, ſo as either to admit, and let ſuch into the Church as are fit for Memberſhip and Communion. This is done by Baptiſm; whereby ſolemn Entrance and Admiſſion into the Church is confer'd, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. or, To Shut, and Lock the Doors againſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> to keep out ſuch as are unfit.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172319:6"/>
            <p n="2">(2) To <hi>Retain Sins,</hi> i. e. Authority to inflict Church-Cenſures, and thereby to exclude or caſt out Scandalous and Impenitent Sinners, who diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be rotten Members, and ſo ſuch as are to be cut off; or at leaſt labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under ſome ſuch dangerous Diſeaſe as requires <hi>Sharpneſs</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10.) and a <hi>Rod</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.21.) and to be purged out (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.) and put away from among them, <hi>v.</hi> 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) To <hi>Remit Sins;</hi> that is, In caſe of Repentance, to abſolve from thoſe Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and reſtore to the Communion of the Church again 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. But in caſe they continue Obſtinate, Impenitent and Incorrigible, then to retain their Sins ſtill, and to deny them this Diſcharge and Abſolution, but continue them ſtill under the Sentence.</p>
            <p>Now, Whether this Power may be called <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> (which <hi>Grotius</hi> vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently deems, and pleads ſtiffly againſt, <hi>de Imperio Sum. Poteſt.</hi> c. 9.) is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial as to the thing it ſelf, ſo long as the forementioned Powers are allow'd.</p>
            <p>What is the firſt Subject of this Power; Whether the whole Church, as the<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Dr.</hi> Owen <hi>of the Church,</hi> p. 72.</note> Independents maintain; or only its Officers, as the<note n="†" place="margin">See Ball<hi>'s Tryal,</hi> p. 234, &amp;c.</note> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians aſſert? And likewiſe, Whether all Miniſters have ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally an equal ſhare of Church-Power? Are weighty and noble Queſtions, which I cannot ſtand to determine now.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Office of a Miniſtry is <hi>ſeparated</hi> from all Lordly Dominion, and Secular Juriſdiction, ſo alſo from all Secular Affairs and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Office of the Miniſtry is <hi>ſeparate</hi> alſo from all Civil Secular Affairs and Employments; whether by way of <hi>Office,</hi> as Juſtices of Peace, Mayors, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables; or by way of <hi>Trade,</hi> as Merchants, Shop-keepers, Graſiers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any other Vocation, as Phyſicians, School-maſters, or the like. A Perſon that devotes himſelf to the Miniſtry, muſt divide himſelf from all theſe as his common Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and particular Calling. What elſe can be the meaning of that Injunction 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Give thy ſelf wholly to them.</hi> (Reading, Exhortation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) And ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereunto was the Practiſe of the Twelve, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4. <hi>We will give our ſelves conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to Prayer, and to the Miniſtry of the Word.</hi> And that they might not be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred therein, they appointed a fort of Perſons, commonly called <hi>Deacons</hi> (tho' how properly I cannot tell, for the Text does not call them ſo) to perform ſome of that Work which they themſelves performed before. And the Apoſtle proves this Point by the caſe of other Callings, or at leaſt by an Example taken from Souldiers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>No Man that Wars, intangles himſelf with the Affairs of this Life, that he may pleaſe him who has choſen him to be a Souldier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo under the Law, the Prieſts were forbidden to defile themſelves for the Dead, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.1. to teach them, <q>and in them all Succeſſive Miniſters of holy things, that they ought ſo intirely to give themſelves to the Service of God, that they ought to renounce all Expreſſions of natural Affection, and <hi>all worldly Employments,</hi> ſo far as they are Impediments to the diſcharge of their Holy Services. <bibl>Pool in loc.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:172319:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But may ſome ſay, notwithſtanding this Separation in the Text, <hi>Paul</hi> after this, wrought with his hands in a Mechanick Trade, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I have ſeveral things to reply.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He puts this into the Catalogue of his Sufferings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was only in caſe of neceſſity; to miniſter unto his Neceſſities, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.34.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He did not make a common Practiſe of it. You never read he did ſo at any other time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thoſe that have His Gifts and extraordinary Abilities, may do ſo too, if there be occaſion for it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It was the Cuſtom of the Jewiſh Nation, to ſet their Children to learn ſome Trade; yea, tho' they were Students, (as I could ſhew by divers paſſages out of the <hi>Talmud</hi>) and accordingly, tho' <hi>Paul</hi>'s Education was ingenuous, in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> yet it ſeems he learn'd this Mechanick Trade of Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making, and ſo upon the occaſion fore-mention'd, makes uſe of it. But one Swallow makes no Summer: One Exception does rather eſtabliſh, confirm and ſtrengthen the general Rule, than weaken it. This then is a general Rule, that a Miniſter's Work is a ſeparate Work from all worldly Affairs and Employments.</p>
            <p>And therefore I cannot approve of their Practiſe, who joyn other Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with the Miniſtry ordinarily; whether it be any thing that is nearer of kin to it, ſo has a tendency thereto; as matters of Learning; or more remote. I can't ſee how they can conſiſt together, but that one muſt needs joſle, and be a hindrance to the other. As no Man can ſerve two Maſters, becauſe he will cleave to the one, and deſpiſe the other; ſo neither can any Man be of two Vocations ſo vaſtly different; for doubtleſs he'll neglect either the one or the other; or at leaſt, not be ſo intirely devoted to the one as he ought to be. How can a Man be ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when he plunges himſelf over head and ears in other Affairs and Buſineſſes. Whatſoever a Man does in any Imployment, he ſhould do it with all his might, (<hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10.) but all his might can't be laid out about two things at once ſo different. The whole Stream can't run in two diſtinct Channels. The Work of a Miniſter is compar'd to that of a Plow-man, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.62. and as he that looks back is unfit for the Kingdom of God; ſo he that looks aſide, or looks off, is like to make but ill-favour'd Work on't. A Plow-man ſhould not Plow with an Oxe and an Aſs together, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.20. nor mingle divers ſorts of Seed, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.19.</p>
            <p>This is the ordinary ſtanding Rule. What may be done in caſes of Neceſſity, when either the People fail of their Duty, in affording their Miniſter a competent comfortable Livelihood, or in Times of Perſecution, I ſay not: Only this I ſay, That Neceſſity ſhould not be pretended where there's none, nor in a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree than is real. Thus much for the firſt General, That the Work of the Miniſtry is a Separate Work.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Secondly, <hi>A Call from God is not ſufficient of it ſelf to inveſt a Perſon into the Office of the Miniſtry, but he muſt be ſolemnly ſet a-part by Man alſo.</hi> Nothing can be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172319:7"/>plainer than this out of theſe words, <hi>I have called them,</hi> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>to ſuch a work,</hi> but <hi>do you ſeparate them.</hi> Whatſoever a Call from God is, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſoever it does conſiſt, yet that is not ſufficient of it ſelf. Could not the Holy Ghoſt here as well have ſeparated them to, and ſet them about their Work, as call'd them to it? Could not he as well have ſaid to <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> Go about ſuch a Work; and that in the ſame way as he ſaid to theſe Prophets and Teachers, <hi>Separate me Barnabas and Saul?</hi> Yes, certainly he could. But he'll honour his own Inſtitutions, and maintain the Credit and Authority of his Officers; for which reaſon he ſends <hi>Cornelius</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> to be inſtructed by him, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.5. and he ſends <hi>Ananias</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> to tell him what he ſhould do, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.11.</p>
            <p>O how Happy would it be for the Church, if all that take upon them this Work of the Miniſtry, could but ſhew a good Call from God, tho' they had no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no Separation or Ordination by Man: But inſtead of this, ſome alledge their Gifts and Abilities; others make uſe of the Election or Call of the People for their Warrant; but neither of theſe have any Foundation in Scripture, as the next Head will evince: But this Head relates only to the Negative part, That a Call from God alone is not ſufficient to make a Man a compleat Miniſter. It was not ſo then, much leſs is it ſo now, when immediate Revelations and Inſpirations are ceaſed, and therefore none that I know of now-a days do pretend to an immediate Call. This is the Second.</p>
            <p n="30">30. Thirdly, <hi>Officers in the Church have Authority from Chriſt to ſet a-part others.</hi> You ſee by what ſteps I proceed: (1) Miniſters muſt be ſet apart. (2) A Call from God is not ſufficient without a Separation by Man. (3) This Separation muſt be performed by Church-Officers, who are authorized by Chriſt hereunto. Thoſe that the Holy Ghoſt here gives this Command unto, were the Prophets and Teachers of the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> v. 1.</p>
            <p>And here I meet with Adverſaries on both hands; the Prelatiſts on the one hand, and ſome Independents and Anabaptiſts on the other. The former plead for and inſiſt upon ſomething more, <hi>viz.</hi> That Ordination muſt be performed by Officers of a Superior Order or Degree to thoſe in the Text: The latter allow of and are content with ſomething leſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt of theſe, It is one of the grand Controverſies of our Age, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Presbyterians and Prelatiſts, Whether this Separation, or Ordination, muſt be perform'd by Biſhops, or may be perform'd by Presbyters; ſo as that it ſhould be of no force, except a Biſhop have a hand in it. That it ſhould be done by Scripture-biſhops, <hi>i.e.</hi> Presbyters, I willingly grant: But the Neceſſity of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of a Dioceſan Biſhop, is that which we deny: So that the great Queſtion is this, Whether it be abſolutely neceſſary to the firm and ſufficient Ordination of a Miniſter, that it be perform'd by the Concurrence, Conſent, Aſſiſtance and Approbation of a Dioceſan Biſhop? or, Whether Ordination perform'd by a company of Presbyters, be not Valid, Firm and Sufficient, tho' there be no Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Biſhop among them? Some high Church-men hold the former, <hi>That the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172319:8"/>Concurrence of a Dioceſan Biſhop is abſolutely neceſſary; and thereby <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchurch moſt of the Reformed Churches to gratifie the Church of</hi> Rome. And hereupon, at that nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Revolution upon the Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. our Biſhops would have all thoſe to be re-ordain'd, that were ordaia'd by Presbyters, during the abſence of the Biſhops, or elſe not to be owned for Miniſters, nor capable of any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Imployment or Preferment.</p>
            <p>But that Ordination, perform'd only by a company of Presbyters, without a Dioceſan Biſhop, is firm and ſufficient, I ſhall prove by Scripture, which is the only Rule we profeſs to walk by, and therefore ſufficient for our purpoſe. My Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-proof is two-fold, by Example, and by Argument.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) We have Scripture-Examples of Ordination perform'd by Presbyters alone <hi>viz.</hi> (1) This of my Text, where you may obſerve, both the <hi>Work</hi> that was done; It was Ordination, perform'd by Faſting, Prayer, and Impoſition of hands, whereby <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> were ſeparated and ſet a-part for their Miniſterial Imployment: And if this be not Ordination, what is? Here is certainly all that is requir'd thereto, if we take our meaſures either from Scripture or all Antiquity, (bating the Preparatives thereto, which are not of this Conſideration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Tho' ſome make Ordination leſs (as we ſhall hear anon) yet none make it more.</p>
            <p>Obſerve alſo the <hi>Perſons</hi> that did this Work of Ordination; who they were that were commanded by the Holy Ghoſt to ordain <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul;</hi> why, they were the Prophets and Teachers here at <hi>Antioch,</hi> v. 1. <hi>i.e.</hi> Such as did not only inſtruct the People, and expound the Scriptures, but had alſo the Prophetick Spirit, and were partakers of Revelations, ſaith Dr. <hi>Lightfoot, Harmony of the New Teſtament,</hi> p. 93. Theſe then, tho' indued with a Spirit of Prophecy, as was both uſual and neceſſary in thoſe times, were the ordinary Paſtors and Teachers of the Church, as the Apoſtle joyns them together, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. which were no other than Presbyters.</p>
            <p>Here then Presbyters do perform this Work of Ordination, and that by the particular Direction and Command of the Holy Ghoſt, and therefore they have power to ordain, and their Ordination is Valid and Sufficient. (2) Another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is of <hi>Timothy,</hi> who was ordain'd by the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Neglect not the Gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> Not of the Office (as ſome would ſhift it off; for the Office has no hands; and beſides the Office is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) but of Perſons in that Office. What can be more expreſs than this? True, <hi>Paul</hi> joyn'd with them (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.) as one of the Ordainers, which he'd never have done, if they had not had Authority to do what they did.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I prove it by this Scripture-Argument, or Reaſon, becauſe Presbyters are Scripture-Biſhops: That Scripture-Biſhops may ordain, I think is queſtion'd by none: But Presbyters are Scripture-Biſhops. This is generally granted both by Preteſtants and Papiſts (except a few high Church-men of late) that the words <hi>[Biſhop]</hi> and <hi>[Presbyter]</hi> are uſed promiſcuouſly in Scripture for the ſame Perſons,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172319:8"/>or Perſons in the ſame Office. <hi>Convenit inter omnes in Apoſtolorum aetate inter Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos &amp; Presbyteros nullum diſcrimen fuiſſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caſſand. Conſult. Art.</hi> 14. <hi>It is agreed among all, that in the Apoſtles times there was no difference between Biſhops and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters. Apud veteres iidem Epiſcopi &amp; Presbyteri fuerunt.</hi> ſaith <hi>P. Lombard. With the Ancients, Biſhops and Presbyters were the ſame.</hi> I could add more to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But that you may not take it upon truſt, but may ſee with your own Eyes, I ſhall make it plain to you by comparing two or three places of Scripture toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Look into <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17, 18. <hi>From Miletus he ſent to Epheſus and called the Elders</hi> (or Presbyters) <hi>of the Church and when they were come to him, he ſaid unto them.</hi> Theſe then are the Perſons to whom he ſpeaks, the Presbyters: Now look into v. 28. and there he tells them, That the Holy Ghoſt has made them Over-ſeers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Biſhops. Theſe Presbyters were Biſhops. Again, Look into <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>I left thee in Crete to ordain Elders</hi> (Presbyters) <hi>in every City.</hi> Then v. 7. <hi>For a Biſhop muſt he blameleſs;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ex hoc loco manifeſtum, eoſdem dici &amp; ſuiſſe Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, qui dicebantur &amp; erant Presbyteri, alias nulla foret in Textu Apoſtolico connectio, quam tamen par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticula <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] diſerte ponit. Quae enim <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> haec foret, Illi conſtituendi ſunt Fresbyteri qui ſunt ſine crimine, quia Epiſcopum (cujus Officium, poteſtas, Juriſdictio &amp; gradus differt a Presbyterio) oportet eſſe ſine crimine? <hi>Ger. de Min. Eccleſ.</hi> From this place it is manifest, that the ſame Perſons were both called and were Biſhops, who were called and were Presbyters: Otherwiſe there would be no Connection in the Apoſtles Diſcourſe; which yet the cauſal Particle [for] expreſly aſſerts. For what coherence would this be, They are to be made Presbyters who are blameleſs, becauſe a Biſhop (whoſe Office, Power, Juriſdiction and Degree, is different from that of a Presbyter) ought to be blameleſs?</note> whom he calls Presbyters in one place, he calls Biſhops in the other.</p>
            <p>Once more, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5, 1. <hi>The Elders which are among you. I exhort</hi>—v. 2. <hi>Feed the Flock of God</hi>—<hi>taking the over-ſight of them.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Biſhoping it,</hi> or playing the Biſhops. Presbyters were made Over-ſeers or Biſhops by the Holy Ghoſt in the <hi>Acts:</hi> Treating of the Ordination of Presbyters, he lays down the Qualifications of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, in <hi>Titus:</hi> the Elders or Presbyters are commanded to exerciſe the Office of a Biſhop in <hi>Peter;</hi> Therefore Presbyters are Scripture-Biſhops, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently may ordain; or, Ordination performed by them is Firm and Sufficient.</p>
            <p>And here I might content my ſelf with this Proof, it being ſufficient for us, that we have Scripture-warrant for what we do. But becauſe <hi>Antiquity</hi> is ſo much inſiſted upon by ſome in this caſe (as King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt ask'd Archb. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Wight, Where he found in Antiquity, That Presbyters alone ordain'd any?</hi>) therefore I ſhall not decline dealing with them at this Weapon; but ſhall joyn Iſſue with them upon this Point alſo; wherein I ſhall only produce the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Teſtimony of two famous Biſhops, the moſt Learned of this Age.</p>
            <p>The firſt is a Paſſage of the renowned Archb.<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> as it is related by <hi>Mr. Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> both in his <hi>Life,</hi> p. 206. and in his <hi>Diſput. of Church-Government,</hi> p. 216. The paſſage is this, <q>I ask'd him (Archb. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>) his Judgment about the Validity of Presbyterian Ordination; which he aſſerted; and told me, That the King ask'd him at the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> Where ever he found in Antiquity, that Presbyters alone ordain'd any?</q> And that he anſwered, <q>I can ſhew your Majeſty more;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172319:9"/>even where Presbyters alone ſucceſſively ordain'd Biſhops, and inſtanc'd in <hi>Jerom</hi>'s words, <hi>Epiſt. ad Evagr.</hi> of the Presbyters of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> chooſing and making their own Biſhops, from the days of <hi>Mark</hi> till <hi>Heraclas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The other is of <hi>Biſhop Stillingfleet,</hi> who proves, by ſeveral Inſtances, that Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters had the intrinſick power of Ordination, but only that it was reſtrain'd by Eccleſiaſtical Laws: and that after Epiſcopal Government was ſetled, yet Ordination by Presbyters was lookt on as valid, <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 379, &amp;c. and then in another place, p. 273. he quotes that very paſſage of <hi>Jerom,</hi> which A. Biſh. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> had done, <hi>Nam &amp; Alexandria a Marco Evangeliſta uſque ad Heraclam &amp; Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium Epiſcopos, Presbyteri ſemper unum ex ſe electum in excelſiori gradu collocatum, Epiſcopum nominabant, quomodo ſi exercitus Imperatorem faciat; aut Diaconi eligant de ſe quem induſtrium noverint, &amp; Archidiaconum vocent. Ep.</hi> 85. <hi>ad Evagr. At Alexandria, from Mark the Evangeliſt to Heraclas and Dionyſius, Biſhops, the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters having choſen one of themſelves, and ſet him in a higher ſtation, called him a Biſhop: as if an Army ſhould chuſe an Emperor; or a Company of Deacons, ſhould chuſe one of themſelves, whom they know to be very diligent, and ſhould call him Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon.</hi> Which Teſtimony he vindicates from ſeveral exceptions that were made againſt it.</p>
            <p>This then may juſtifie our practiſe this day againſt all Gainſayers; that we who are Presbyters, and have no Dioceſan Biſhop among us, yet undertake to perform this work of Ordination; ſince, as you have ſeen, we have good ground and warrant for it, both from <hi>Scripture,</hi> and from <hi>Antiquity.</hi> To which might be added the Conſent of all Reformed Churches: but that I muſt haſten.</p>
            <p>Hence alſo we may ſee the intolerable Uſurpation of thoſe who would not allow the Ordination by Presbyters (even in thoſe times, when, either there were no Biſhops, or they durſt not be known) to be lawful and ſufficient. But do but obſerve the partiality of theſe Men: They that would not allow Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by Presbyters in <hi>England,</hi> or any other Reform'd Church, to be valid, yet would allow Ordination in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (though their Biſhops be ſo far from being the true Miniſters of Chriſt, that they are the Slaves and Limbs of Antichriſt; though their Ordination be attended with ſo many Fopperies and Superſtitious Ceremonies, and though the perſons be never ſo unfit) yet becauſe one that has the Title of a Biſhop has a hand in it, therefore that muſt be valid, forſooth, and all others invalid and null. <q>Let a Perſon Ordain'd by Presbyters be never ſo well qualify'd, never ſo faithful in the diſcharge of his Office; let another Perſon, Ordain'd by a Biſhop, be never ſo defective in qualifications, let him be never ſo prophane in his Life, yet this Man muſt paſs for a true Miniſter, becauſe he has the ineffectual Bleſſing of a Biſhop, and the other a meer Uſurper, and all his Adminiſtrations muſt be null and void for want of this Ceremony. <bibl>
                     <hi>Owen of Ordination, p.</hi> 86.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This plainly ſhows what Friends ſuch are to the Reformation, how highly they value the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and what dirt they caſt in the face, and upon the practice of all Reform'd Churches.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:172319:9"/>
            <p>Thus I have, I hope, pretty well acquitted my ſelf from theſe Adverſaries. But there are ſome others, though not ſo conſiderable, that I muſt ſpeak a word unto; who, inſtead of this Ordination by Church-Officers, ſet up two things in its Room, <hi>Gifts,</hi> and a <hi>Call from the People.</hi> I ſhall ſpeak briefly to both.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Gifts and Abilities are not ſufficient to give a Man a Title to the Office of the Miniſtry; 'tis ſo in no caſe whatſoever. There's no inſtance in the World that I can think of, from the King on the Throne to a petty Conſtable, or Surveyor of the High-ways, or any other thing whatſoever that hath the Nature of an Office in the Commonwealth, that a bare qualification and ability for it doth inable a Man to take upon him the diſcharge of it. Much leſs then ſhould it be ſo in the Church, where all things ſhould be moſt regular and orderly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. and where the leaſt miſcarriage is dangerous, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. Hence even Chriſt himſelf, tho' fill'd with Wiſdom, when but a Child (<hi>Luke</hi> 2.40.) in whom were hidden all the treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. yet did not thruſt himſelf into the Office of a Prieſt, till called as <hi>Aaron,</hi> as the Apoſtle obſerves, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.5. Now <hi>Aaron</hi> had not only a particular deſignation and appointment by God to this Office, but was actually put into it, and ſetled in it by <hi>Moſes, Levit.</hi> 8. and 9. So Chriſt was not only call'd by an immediate voice from God the Father, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17 but was Anointed, as it were, by <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt in his Baptiſm, and thereby Inveſted and Inſtalled into this Office. Wheupon the Apoſtle lays down this General Rue, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. <hi>No man takes</hi> (viz. legally and duly) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> or office (whatſoever his parts and abilities be) <hi>but he that is called of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much is generally granted by all, except a few ſelf-conceited perſons that think better of themſelves than any body elſe doth, and ſo turn Self-ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. They can ſcarce be ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe they have generally little or no Learning, but however they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; they lay hands (I don't ſay, violent hands) upon themſelves, and ſo become guilty of a ſort of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; tho' not in the worſt ſenſe of that word. But, if every Phaeton that thinks himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, may be permitted to drive the Charriot of the Sun, no wonder if the World be ſet on fire, ſaith Mr. <hi>Vines.</hi> Well then, Gifts won't ſerve turn.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither hath the Election of the People any more power, virtue or efficacy in it to make a Man a Miniſter. No Authority can be deriv'd from them; for <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil dat quod non habet.</hi> All their Intereſt about a Miniſter conſiſts only in making choice of ſuch a Perſon for the Exerciſe of his Miniſtry among 'em; which is quite a diſtinct thing from Ordination, or making a Man to be a Miniſter in General, or confering the Office of a Miniſter upon him. This appears plainly by that place, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2, 3. <hi>The Twelve called the multitude of the diſciples to 'em, and ſaid, Look you out among you ſeven Men of honeſt report, whom we my appoint over this buſineſs.</hi> They were only to <hi>look out,</hi> no nominate, to fix upon the Perſons who were fit for ſuch an Employment, and then the Apoſtles were to <hi>appoint</hi> 'em: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The word frequently ſignifies to <hi>authorize,</hi> or <hi>inveſt with authority;</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45, 47. and 25.23. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.10, 27, 35. and is tranſlated to <hi>Ordain, Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>I left
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172319:10"/>thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldſt</hi>—<hi>Ordain Elders in every City.</hi> This the Apoſtles reſerv'd to themſelves, as belonging to them; to appoint, ordain, authorize. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Nomination and Election was the Diſciples work, Ordination was the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. And mark it, this work that they were here Ordain'd unto, was a work of an inferior nature to the Miniſtry, viz. <hi>Serving of Tables,</hi> v. 2. Now if they might not take upon 'em, without the ſpecial Inveſtiture and Admiſſion of the Apoſtles, much leſs might they have undertaken the work of the Miniſtry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. It's without all warrant from Scripture that the People ſhould make a Miniſter. There's neither <hi>Precept,</hi> nor <hi>Preſident</hi> for it in all the N. T. We read of Ordination by Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3. and 14.23. by Prophets and Teachers; in my Text, by Evangeliſts, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. and by Presbyters, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. but for Ordination by the People, we meet not at all with it: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is obſervable, that all that is written in any of the Epiſtles about Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, is in thoſe to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> who were Officers; in the others, which were written to the Churches, there's no mention made of theſe things; which is a convincing proof that the work of Ordination is a work belonging to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and not to the People, ſay the <hi>London</hi>-Divines.</p>
            <p>See this Point largely handled in <hi>Jus Div. Min. Evang. part</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Thus, I hope, I have kept my ground, and defended my Poſition from all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks made upon it, either on the right hand, or on the left, <hi>That Officers in the Church, and they only, have Authority from Chriſt to ſet apart others for the work of the Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Now I proceed to the laſt Head of Diſcourſe, concerning the <hi>Manner</hi> of this <hi>Separation,</hi> or Ordination, that it muſt be done by Faſting, Prayer, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands.</p>
            <p>That Faſting and Prayer muſt be uſed upon this occaſion, is granted by all. There can be no queſtion made of it. The weightineſs of the work requires it. All the doubt is concerning Impoſition of hands. Therefore to clear that, I ſhall ſhew as briefly as I can, (1) The <hi>Original,</hi> (2) The <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> (3) The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of it in this caſe, (4.) Whoſe hands are to be Impos'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Original of this Rite or Ceremony, it was uſed upon ſeveral occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Thoſe that belong not to our preſent purpoſe I ſhall paſs by.</p>
            <p>The firſt place where it was us'd for a ſetting apart, or Ordaining to an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, is <hi>Num.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt bring the Levites before the Lord, and the children of Iſrael ſhall put their hands upon the Levites,</hi> and then v. 14. <hi>Thus ſhalt thou ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Levites from among the children of Iſrael.</hi> Here was a Separation for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Employment: and this was directed to be done by the children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> which cannot poſſibly be meant of the whole Congregation (that was impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) and therefore muſt be underſtood only of ſome of 'em: but then the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, Who theſe [ſome] were that were commanded to impoſe their hands on 'em: and here Interpreters are divided. Some underſtand 'em of the Princes and Chiefs of each Tribe, who by this Ceremony ſignify'd their intire reſignation and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172319:10"/>of them to God's Service. This Senſe Mr. <hi>Pool</hi> prefers as the beſt: But I rather think it muſt be meant of the Firſt-born (who ſupplied the place of the Prieſts before) in whoſe ſtead the Levites were taken, v. 16-18. <hi>For they</hi> (the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites) <hi>are wholly given unto me from among the Children of Iſrael: inſtead of ſuch as open every Womb, even inſtead of the Firſt-born of all the Children of Iſrael have I taken them unto me. For all the Firſt-born of the Children of Iſrael are mine, both of Man and Beaſt: on the day that I ſmote every Firſt-born in the Land of Egypt, I ſanctified them for my ſelf. And I have taken the Levites for all the Firſt-born of the Children of Iſrael.</hi> Whence it ſeems much more likely to me, that theſe were the Perſons that laid their hands on the Heads of the Levites, than the Princes or any other, even as he that brought a Burnt-offering, was to put his hand upon the head of it, <hi>Lv.</hi> 1.4. to note, his laying his Sins upon it, and offering it up in his own ſtead So here, The Levites being taken inſtead of the Firſt-born, To whom did it more properly belong to lay their hands on them, than to the Firſt-born?</p>
            <p>This is the firſt Example of this kind; after which it was commonly made uſe of in ſetting apart to any Sacred Function.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of Impoſition of Hands in Ordination, I prove by theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) Becauſe all Scripture Examples of Ordination were performed with this Ceremony, and none without it. None is, or can be produced. We have Scripture-warrant for it, but none for the neglect of it: Therefore to thoſe that profeſs to walk by Scripture-Rule, this ſhould be ſufficient. As we muſt not add to Scripture-Inſtitutions by our own Inventions, ſo neither muſt we detract, or take from Scripture, by neglecting any thing we have Scripture-warrant for.</p>
            <p>Nay more than this,</p>
            <p n="2">(2) We have an expreſs Command for it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no Man,</hi> where the Negative includes the Affirmative. As it forbids the denying of it raſhly and unadviſedly, ſo it enjoyns the doing of it conſiderately and deliberately.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) Becauſe the ſpecial Nature of Ordination doth conſiſt in this Ceremony; as appears, Becauſe the Spirit of God in Scripture expreſſes the whole Work of Ordination, by this one Act of Impoſition of Hands; as in the place laſt quoted, and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. Yea not only ſo, but the whole Work of the Miniſtry is couch'd under this Expreſſion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. as the moſt judicious and ſolid Interpreters do underſtand it.</p>
            <p>By all which the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> hereof appears in this caſe. And yet it's well known that ſome Perſons, tho' ſometimes they will admit of it, yet lay no ſtreſs upon it; don't count it a neceſſary part of Ordination, but think it may be as valid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it as with it; and accordingly do frequently omit it. From whence we may take notice of the unevenneſs of ſome Mens Conſciences, or of their Practice at leaſt; which is like Indentures, ſometimes up, ſometimes down. They require poſitive ſigns of Grace in thoſe they admit to be Members: They inſiſt upon a Church-Covenant to be ent'red into by them: They admit Ordination by the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172319:11"/>People; which things have no Foundation in Scripture. On the other ſide, they reject, or at leaſt, neglect Impoſition of hands in Ordination, tho' there be ſuch plain Scripture-warrant for it, as you have ſeen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The next thing to be ſpoken unto, is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of this Ceremony. It ſerves for divers Ends.</p>
            <p n="1">(1) To convey unto, and beſtow upon, the Perſon receiving it the Office of a Presbyter. This is the principal Uſe of it. So it was with <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> in the Text; they were hereby ſeparated to the Work of the Miniſtry among the Gentiles. So it was with <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Neglect not the Gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> By <hi>[Gift]</hi> here, the<note n="*" place="margin">The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is often taken, not only for the Grace by which we are fitted for an Office, but for an Office to wich Men thro' Grace are fitted.</note> Office of the Miniſtry is generally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: This was <hi>given,</hi> or conveigh'd to him by Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) It ſerves to deſign the particular Perſon that is ſet apart for this Office. While Prayer is only made for this purpoſe, poſſibly many Perſons in the Congregation may not know who it is particularly that is meant, but when hands come to be laid upon him, or them, then every one ſees who it is.</p>
            <p n="3">(3) Thereby the Perſon is dedicated, conſecrated, and offer'd up to the Lord and his Service; as it was uſed in the Old Teſtament for this End, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4) It's uſed as an Authoritative and Miniſterial Benediction of the Perſon ordain'd; as it was uſed by <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 48.14. and by Chriſt in his Bleſſing and Praying over the little Children, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whoſe Hands are to be impoſed? Not the Hands of any of the People; which ſome<note n="†" place="margin">In ſuch Churches where there are no El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Impoſition of Hands may be perform'd by ſome of the Brethren choſen by the Church thereunto. <hi>Platform of Church-Diſcipline,</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> allow of when there are no Elders or Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters to be had: But that is a caſe ſcarce to be ſuppoſed, and therefore nothing follows upon it. Certainly ſuch may be had ſomewhere or other. There is no warrant at all in Scripture, for any to lay on Hands in Ordination, but Church-Officers. Nothing like a Proof is alledg'd, but only that place, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8.10. but that muſt needs be meant of the Firſt-born, who were the Prieſts in each Family; as I ſhew'd even now. No; theſe have no power to do it: It muſt be done by Church-Officers: So it was herein the Text, and ſo in all other places where it is mention'd; as I proved before.</p>
            <p>Thus I have both aſſerted and maintain'd, the Lawfulneſs and Warrantable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Validity and Sufficiency of our Practice this day, and alſo vindicated it from the Cavils and Exceptions of Adverſaries on either hand; ſo that I hope you are all fully ſatisfied, that we don't take more upon us, than we have good ground in Scripture for: That we don't remove any ancient Land-marks: That we don't <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Intrench upon the Rights of others, but keep within the Bounds God has fixed and preſcribed to us, and ſo may lawfully proceed to the Work that further remains to be done by us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:172319:11"/>
            <head>The Exhortation.</head>
            <div type="address_to_the_minister">
               <p>BEloved in our Lord! I begin the concluding part of the Solemn Work of this day, with the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.22. <hi>I beſeech you Brethren, ſuffer the word of Exhortation;</hi> which I ſhall direct, firſt to you, who have been ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſet apart to the Office and Work of the Miniſtry, by the laying on of the Hands of the Presbytery, accompanied with Faſting, Prayer and Bleſſing; and then to you the People.</p>
               <p>That which now, Sir, I am to entertain you with, is, That you would ſeriouſly conſider the Greatneſs of your Office and Work: How weighty your Calling is, above all others, which hath ſo near a relation to the Purpoſe of the Father, the Purchaſe of his Son, and the Charge of the Holy Spirit. To you is committed <hi>the Word of Reconciliation;</hi> your God hath counted you Faithful, put you into the Miniſtry, and intruſted you with what highly concerns his own Glory, and the Everlaſting Happineſs of Precious Souls. <hi>Oh take heed to your ſelf, and to all the Flock, over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhop, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own Blood,</hi> Acts 20.28.</p>
               <p>Your principal Work is, to <hi>Preach the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.17. Miniſterially to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the Will of God to his Church, Soundly to Interpret, Expound and Apply the Scriptures to their Edification, and eſpecially to <hi>Preach Chriſt to them.</hi> This is moſt Profitable both for them and your ſelf; This is moſt Weelcome and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and the readieſt way to break their Hearts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Luther</hi> at his Death thus Pray'd, <hi>Thee, O Chriſt, have I known, Thee have I loved, Thee have I taught, Thee have I truſted, and now into thy hands do I commend my Spirit.</hi> The Name of Chriſt in a Sermon, makes the Preaching Sweeteſt. You are not to be a legal Preacher, to preach Salvation by keeping of the Law; yet you are to preach the Law a <hi>Rule of Obedience,</hi> as a means to diſcover Sin, and convince Men of their Miſery out of Chriſt, as a <hi>School-maſter to draw to Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.24. Which is God's ordinary way to prepare to the receiving of Chriſt. So preach the Law, that you may preach the Goſpel, for that Preaching is beſt which drives to Chriſt; and he is the beſt Preacher, not that tickles the Ear, but breaks the Heart to ſeek after Chriſt, the Phyſician of Souls.</p>
               <p>Labour to preach with all Plainneſs and Perſpicuity to the meaneſt, ſet off your good Notions in the moſt obvious plain Expreſſions. The greateſt Learning is ſeen in the greateſt Plainneſs. The Learned Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi> did ſpread his Net that he might catch the Fiſh. <hi>Non Rhetorice, ſed Apoſtolice, non quanta Eloquentia, ſed Evidentia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Clearneſs and Perſpicuity is the Grace of Speech; painted Glaſs-windows hinder the Light. The <hi>Perſian</hi> Roſes were marr'd with the Sweetneſs of Perfumes. An Iron Key will unlock, where a Wedge of Gold will not; the Fooliſhneſs of Preaching, tho' not Fooliſh Preaching Saves. The Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> were thrown down, not by golden Trumpets, but Rams<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horns.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172319:12"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Brazen Serpent cured, when <hi>Aaron</hi>'s golden Calf brought Death. Stars give Light, when Clouds darken. Plate and Silver Spoons in a Country Fair, are only gazed on, and ſcarce cheapen'd, when wooden Spoons are bought. That Glaſs is beſt, not which is curiouſly wrought, but ſhews the trueſt Face; Good Corn is more eligible than gay Weeds. Naked Truth is moſt beautiful, ſhe needs not outward adorning to make her amiable; and if ſhe appears in finer Cloaths, it is more for Modeſty than Gaudineſs. Mingle not your Water with God's Wine; ſtuff not the Sincere Milk with the Mocks and Hairs of your Fancy. Thoſe Flowers are beſt and ſweeteſt that grow in the Garden, not in the Wilderneſs. Chriſt taught his Diſciples as they were able to hear and bear. Drive according to the Pace of your People. It is the greateſt Art to make dark things plain. Study rather <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> than <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to approve your ſelf a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, than an Artiſt: Soar not aloft to work a vain Admiration in the ignorant Hearers. Prefer a careleſs Plainneſs before an elaborate affected Quaintneſs. Yet let not your Expreſſions be undecent, unſeemly, or undigeſted. <hi>Eſt aliqua frondium Gloria,</hi> the Leaves give ſome beauty to the Trees. <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Bells were golden, ſounding pleaſantly. A naſty Candleſtick is unſuitable to a bright Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and unhandſome Cloaths do not become a fair Body. Truth loves to be plain, but not Sluttiſh. Neither would I have your Sermons to be like empty Tracts, that have a Flood of Words, and a Drop of Matter. <hi>Multa loquantur &amp; nihil dicunt.</hi> Some ſpeak much and ſay nothing, becauſe little or nothing to the purpoſe. I am againſt the Abuſe, not the uſe of Humane Authors, Tongues, Arts and Sciences, theſe are Keys to unlock the Scriptures. Competent Learning is requiſite in a Miniſter, a blind Seer is a Soleciſm. A Miniſter ought to have Skill in the Originals, that he may not ſee only with other Mens Eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor take all upon report and truſt, <hi>John</hi> 4.42. yet Tongues without Arts and Sciences, are but empty Veſſels, mere ſounds. But eſpecially a Miniſter ſhould be mighty in the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16. theſe are the Fountains, and the Foundation you muſt build upon. There is more Light in the Sun than in the Stars, more Water in the Fountain than in the Streams, more Honey in a Barrel of Honey, than in a few ſcatter'd Flowers; and it is good digging for Gold in the Mines of Gold. In Preaching, deliver the whole revealed Will of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27. and nothing but his Will, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. receive what you deliver, and deliver what you receive, eſpecially concerning the Way and Means of Salvation by Chriſt, and Chriſt alone, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.7, 8. Affect not No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, too many Falſe Opinions have inſinuated themſelves, by the uſe of Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Phraſes, and the Affectation of new Light and new Language, hath in theſe days greatly deſtroy'd Practical Godlineſs, and the Power of Religion. Some render 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Be <hi>Affectionate</hi> and <hi>Cordial,</hi> let the Truths you deliver, proceed from an Heart experimentally acquainted with them. That Sermon which is feelingly Preach'd is moſt likely to be effectual. <hi>Quod procedit a corde, redit in Cor.</hi> When you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172319:12"/>have once affected your ſelf, you are in a fair way to affect others. Be you, as <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, a Burning and Shining Light, firſt burn inwardly, then ſhine out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in your Doctrine, and ſo yon you'll ſpeak in the Evidence and Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit and Power.</p>
               <p>Be <hi>faithful, Jer.</hi> 23.28. Call not evil good, nor good evil, neither make the heart of the righteous ſad, nor ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked. Suppreſs not, omit not any needful truths, or reproofs, out of fear or favour, Preach not pleaſing things out of flattery, or deſire to get favour. This undoes the Souls of people, eſpecially at their Deaths, and this ſin will lye heavy on the Miniſter's Conſcience when he lies a dying. Speak the word with boldneſs, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.29. Be zealous with intention of affection and ſpeech. Cry aloud, ſpare not, &amp;c. ſave them with fear, pull them out of the fire. Fire ſate upon the Tongues of the Diſciples when the Holy Ghoſt came upon them. And <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Tongue, touch'd by an Angel, was not dipt in water, but tipt with fire, and fire came out of the Mouths of the Two Witneſſes. Be not the Sugar and Honey, but Salt of the Word. There is need of this Fire to heat, of this Hammar to break, of this Sword to fetch blood, conſidering the coldneſs, ſtonineſs, and hardneſs of peoples hearts. He is the beſt Chyrurgion, or Phyſitian, not that puts his Patient to leaſt pain, but that cures and heals. Yet zeal and love may ſtand together, for zeal is the blood and ſpirits of love. Mingle not your own paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with your zeal, vent them not to diſgrace others, or eaſe your own Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. Mingle not ſtrange fire with God's fire. That <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, <hi>James</hi> 3.14. becomes not a Miniſter who ſhould be gentle among his People, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7, 11. Come with love in your heart, and uſe expreſſions of love in your ſpecches. The Bee carries Honey in her mouth, as well as a ſting about her. Paſſion may raiſe the blood, but compaſſion will turn the bowels. Pills wrapt in Sugar go the better down, and Nailes dipt in Oyl drive the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. Weeping tears are the blood and ſpirits of Love, and thoſe having glazed his eyes, the bowels of Compaſſions that lay at his heart affected with their miſery were ſeen as in ſo many Looking-glaſſes. Every Diſh is ſprinkled with Salt, yet ſomething elſe beſides Salt is ſet upon the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Wiſely put a difference between perſons and perſons in your Reproofs, as alſo between ſinners and ſinners; ſuch as ſin of weakneſs, reſtore with a ſpirit of meekneſs; and ſuch as ſin of wilfulneſs rebuke ſharply, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, cuttingly; ſecret ſins reprove ſecretly, and more open, rebuke more openly; yet ſo, as (if you can) to hide the Perſon, and diſcover only his ſin; aiming not at his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation, but Reformation: reprove ſin in all, but perſonate none: ſhew your zeal againſt the ſin, yet manifeſt your love to the Perſon.</p>
               <p>In Preaching, aim not only at your own glory, applauſe or credit; as you are a friend of, ſo you muſt ſue for the Bridegroom, not your ſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>John</hi> 3.29, 30. Pride is a ſin that ſticks cloſe to the beſt. A Veſſel is eaſily emptied of Water, but not of Aire; the better parts and gifts are, and performances
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172319:13"/>come off, the more ſubject to be proud of them. The fineſt Cloth is moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Moths, and with ſweeteſt Flowers Men are ſooneſt Perfum'd. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Honey, tho' ſweet, was not offer'd in Sacrifice, becauſe it would bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble up. The better your Sermons are, and the more pains you take, if you are proud of them, the greater is your ſin, becauſe you rob God of the more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and you take great pains to purchaſe great miſery. Approbation may be the reſult of your work, and with this the Lord crown your Labours, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage your faithfulneſs, yet this is not to be your primary intention, or ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end, which is too often the ſin of young Divines. Truſt God with your Credit, Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſeek his Glory, and carry on the intereſt of Souls, and he will honour you here ſo far as he ſees good for you, and eternally in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>You are alſo to <hi>Chatechiſe</hi> the young among your People diligently, to Inſtruct the Babes, and faithfully to Teach the Simple. It is your duty plainly and briefly to handle the Fundamental Points of Religion by way of Catechiſm to the Ignorant, this will much facilitate Religion to them, when they ſee the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and end of Divine Truths. Lay a Foundation before you begin to Build, this is the nobleſt and hardeſt work, fit for a Maſter-builder, and makes a well-grounded People; Veſſels ſeaſon'd with the Water of Life, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſavour thereof till old Age.</p>
               <p>Both the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of the New Teſtament are to be Adminiſtred by you. As to the Lord's-Supper, be tender, and walk according to Goſpel-rule, that you be not partaker of other Mens ſins, nor pollute that Sacred Ordinance, by giving it to the groſly ignorant, ſcandalous or prophane.</p>
               <p>As a faithful Shepherd often viſit your Flock, that you may know their ſtates, how things ſtand between God and their Souls, and give them ſuitable, ſavoury, and profitable Advices. Wo to all Careleſs Non-reſidents, by their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from, or negligence when preſent among their People.</p>
               <p>You have, Sir, given a good account of your Learning and Sufficiency, yet let me tell you, that you are ſtill to <hi>give attendance to Reading, to meditate on theſe things, and give your ſelf wholly to them, that your profiting may appear to all Men,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. Your Time and Parts are not your own, but, under God, your Peoples, and to be imploy'd for their profit. Believe it, you'l find your lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings-out will be conſiderable, therefore your layings-in had need be anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Make uſe of your own Underſtanding, neglect not your own Parts, but labour, by Studying, Reading and Praying hard, that you may be throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht to every good work; content not your ſelf with a few Baskets full of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Meat, but ſtrive to be able, on all occaſions, to bring forth out of your Treaſury, things both new and old.</p>
               <p>Your head and heart muſt be at work, and both applyed to this Implopment. If you would be Faithful, you muſt mind the Work of the Miniſtry; and make it appear, that both in your Preparation for, and Execution of your Office,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172319:13"/>you labour in the Word and Doctrine. You have gotten a Cure, therefore muſt not live without care, you are God's Seeds-man to ſow the Seed of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life in the Hearts of your People, and you muſt do it in the Morning, and in the Evening not with-hold your hand. You are God's Husband-man, and this People are your Tillage: <hi>Redit labor actus in orbem.</hi> Your work goes round in a circle, 'tis never at an end, Spring, Summer, Autumn, Winter, no vacation in any. You are painfully to Labour in your Study for your Publick work, to provide as, <hi>David</hi> did, for the Houſe of God, even with all your might. The Portion allotted to the Prieſt under the Law, was the Breaſt and Shoulder. God will not bleſs your Idleneſs, but Endevours, any thing may not ſerve your turn, wherewith to fill the hour. God wrought ſix days for your example, two or three hours on a Saturday-night will not excuſe you. Curſed is he that doth the Work of the Lord negligently. There are ſome that are offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and caſt an evil Eye upon diligent Preachers, becauſe their labouriouſneſs condemns their lazineſs. So great and difficult is your Work, that even <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, who is ſufficient for theſe things; <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, it is <hi>Onus angelicis humeris ormindandum.</hi> How many have ſpent themſelves, waſted their Lungs, and Lives in this labourious Work, the Labour of the Brain and Mind, far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the greateſt bodily Labour; Witneſs the large Volums of the Fathers and Moderns, which were ſo many Monuments of their unwearyed Pains. You muſt Labour for the Pulpit, and in the Pulpit, Labour in the Study before you ſpeak, the Labour of Zeal and Love in ſpeaking; and the Labour of Suffering after ſpeaking, no danger ſo great as Spiritual, therefore no care muſt be ſo great as Miniſterial. Your care muſt be for them who do not, and with them who do care for themſelves. As much as lyes in you, be ready to Preach the Goſpel, be glad to ſpend, and be ſpent in this Service, Work the Work of him that hath ſent you in the Lord. Be inſtant, ſtick cloſe to the Work, Preach the Word in Seaſon, out of Seaſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in a good Seaſon, on the Lord's-Day, the particular ſeaſon appointed for the Preaching of the Word, and out of Seaſon, at other ſeaſonable times, beſides that ſet-time, as occaſion is offered, taking all opportunities of doing good. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to drink a little Wine for his Stomachs ſake, but not to Preach but a little for his Healths ſake, ſurely a Miniſter cannot be ſpent better than thus to waſt himſelf to ſave the Souls of others. Remember what <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> Bp. <hi>Jewel</hi> and Dr. <hi>John Raynolds</hi> ſaid of Dying, Praying, or Preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your work is of Infinite conſequence, your time is exceeding ſhort, and precious, and your Reward is glorious and Eternal. Look, Sir, look on this People, behold the Souls of many wounded, bleeding, dying, and let your eye affect your Heart! Did Chriſt die, and weep and bleed for Souls, and will not you ſweat for Souls? Is it not a fearful thing to be guilty of the Blood of Souls? Will you prefer your idleneſs before the Salvation of the Peoples Souls? What pains did <hi>Jacob</hi> take in feeding of his Flock of Sheep? He regarded not the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172319:14"/>heat of the day, nor the cold of the night nor want of his ſleep, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. Do not the Prophets denounce woes againſt idle and Idol Preachers? Doth not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, Wo be to me if I Preach not the Goſpel. Was not the ſlothful ſervant that hid his Talent in a Napkin, condemned? What is your labour and condeſcenſion to Chriſt's, when he debaſed himſelf, is it not your honour to be imployed in ſeeking and laving theſe that are loſt? How can you think to be ſaved by the Blood of Chriſt your ſelf, if you make light of Souls that are the purchaſe of his Blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Expect, Sir, to meet with many diſcouragments, and dangers, much hardſhip and oppoſition, Bears and Lyons in your way, Storms and Tempeſts in your Voyages. But remember you have this day profeſſed a good profeſſion before many Witneſſes, you have Sworn your ſelf a Soldier, yea, Officer of the Lord of Hoſts, you have liſted your ſelf in his Muſter-roll, entred your Name as a Volunteer, and promiſed to Live and Die in his Quarrel: Oh, reſolve rather to Die with, than to deny him; fly not from your Colours, forſake not your Captain, go not out of God's Bleſſing into the warm Sun, but endure hardſhip as a good Soldier of Jeſus Chriſt. Leave not that Service which you have choſen and liked, as in all things the beſt; Know that good is your Cauſe, better is your Crown and beſt of all is your Captain, to whom keep cloſe, and he will bring you off with Triumph, either keep you ſafe on Earth, or take you ſafe to Heaven.</p>
               <p>Like a good Shepherd ſhew your Flock a good Example, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. Lead it as they in the Eaſtern Countrys, who drove not their Flocks before, but the Sheep followed them. Let your Life and Doctrine go together, and not croſs each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Say as <hi>Gideon</hi> to his Soldiers, look on me, and do Likewiſe. Be a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light in your Sermons, and a ſhining Light in your Converſation. Joyn the <hi>Bell</hi> of Preaching, and the <hi>Pomegranate</hi> of Practiſing together. Have your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> Purity of Doctrine, and <hi>Thummim</hi> Sanctity of Life, walk in the right way your ſelf, in which you are <hi>Mercury</hi> to direct others. <hi>Aaron</hi>'s ſign of being called to the Prieſthood, was a Fruit-bearing Rod. The Cloven Tongues of the Apoſtles, had, as it were, Fingers on them to ſhew and teach them, that their Words ſhould be their Works. It is the note of a bad Man, but mark of a good Miniſter, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.13. to <hi>ſpeak with his feet,</hi> hence <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. How beautiful are the feet of thoſe that Preach the Goſpel of Peace, not only their Tongues, their Speaking, but their Feet, their walking? and <hi>teach with his Fingers.</hi> I would not have to be <hi>vox et praeteura nihil,</hi> yet <hi>tota vox,</hi> that your People may ſee your Voice acting in your Converſation, and ſay, as we have heard, ſo we have ſeen. You are an Angel in this reſpect, becauſe you ſhould have hands under your wings, and ſhould be as an Angel in your life, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of other Men. But if an Angel falls, he turns a Devil. You are called a Star, and ſhould be an Ornament in the Heaven of the Church, but if you are Erratick, they that walk by your Guidance, will be apt to wander. Oh, then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172319:14"/>let it be your care to be holy as Angels, yea, God himſelf is holy in all manner of Converſation, walk with God in your Cloſet, Family, Words and Speeches, be ſober and gracious, forgetful of injuries, ſlow to Anger, patient in Afflictions, ready to do good to all, but hurt to none, and a companion of them that fear the Lord. Your converſation is narrowly looked into, for you are as a City ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Hill; a little ſpot is ſoon ſeen, a little hole is ſoon ſpy'd in your Coat, yea, if there be none, there are thoſe that will make one if they can. A Wart a Mole, the leaſt blemiſh in the face is perſpicuous and apparent to all.</p>
               <p>You are called to draw near unto God, and, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be with God, as it were, in the Mounts therefore had need be holy, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Forehead had Holineſs to the Lord written upon it, when he ſtood before the Lord, and none could be made a Prieſt that had any Blemiſh. <hi>Joſhua</hi> the High-Prieſt was commanded to put off his filthy Garments before he ſtood before the Lord. Unclean hands are not fit to carry God's Ark. How holy had he need be that draws near to ſo Holy a God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14, 15. Alas, who is he to ſpeak to God, and live? Nay, to ſpeak from God to the People, that they may live?</p>
               <p>Would you Preach with Authority, Practice that your ſelf which you Preach to others. Chriſt Taught with Authority, and not as the Scribes, becauſe he did and taught, he Taught by Example as well as Precept, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1. Then there is life in your Doctrine, when there is Doctrine in your life. <hi>Suadet loquentis vita, non oratio.</hi> Life Oratory is moſt powerful. But words have little power, when our lives are contrary. <hi>Dicta factis deficientibus erubeſcant.</hi> Words bluſh when Deeds fail. <hi>Quid verba audiam! cum facta non video.</hi> He that lives contrary to his Preaching, proſtitutes his authority, forfeits his own credit, and his hearers belief of what he Preacheth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He who lives looſly, hath <hi>Jacobs</hi> Voice, and <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands, who acts a double part, of a Saint in the Pulpit, of a Sinner out of it, tempts the People thus juſtly to argue, if what he Speaks be true, why doth he not practice it? If he lives aright, why doth he not Preach it? A ſuitable Living and Converſation will gain and uphold the Credit and Reputation of a Miniſter and his Preaching. This raiſeth even in Wicked Men ſometimes, a reverent and high eſteem of the work of the Miniſtry, and of the Perſon for the Works ſake, as in <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Samuel, Ahab</hi> to <hi>Elias, Joaſh</hi> to <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt. An exemplary Life is a good preſervative againſt Contempt, or at worſt a ground of Comfort in it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as an unſuitable Converſation expoſes a Miniſters Perſon and Office to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Scorn. Wholſom Meat comming out of a foul Diſh is loathed, the wicked Lives of <hi>Eli's</hi> Sons, made the People abhor the Offerings of the Lord. The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> would not receive good Counſel from a debautch Perſon till the ſame was given by one of a grave carriage. <hi>Cujus vita deſpititur, Ejus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatio contemnitor,</hi> Gregory. Sins of Teachers are teaching Sins. <hi>Praecepta docent, exempla movent.</hi> Hence under the Law as great a Sacrifice was offered for the Sins of the Miniſter, as of the whole Congregation. <hi>Lev.</hi> 4.3.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:172319:15"/>
               <p>Without this holy exemplary Life, how ſhall you ſave your own Souls, and thoſe that hear you? but while you Preach to others, your ſelf may prove a Caſt-away; and it may be truly ſaid of you, what was falſly ſaid of Chriſt, You ſaved others, your ſelt you could not ſave: So the Carpenters who built an Ark for <hi>Noah,</hi> which ſaved others, were drowned themſelves. So the Sea-mark may rot it ſelf, which gives others warning to avoid Shipwreck. So <hi>Moſes</hi> brought the People to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but enter'd not himſelf. So <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Lyon had Honey in his Belly, which refreſhed others, but not himſelf. Such a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Sermon to others will witneſs againſt himſelf, and make his Judgment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, when his own Mouth ſhall condemn him, and his own lips bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt him. Take then the Counſel given, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. I refer you to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.—<hi>Tit.</hi> 1. So carry your ſelf, that you may have a good report of them that are without, that your very Adverſaries may ſay, This is a fit Man for this Sacred Sanction, and may be converted by your example. Let not your Works give your Words the Lye, but Preach as powerfully by your Life as by your Lips. Do not only, as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith, <hi>magna loqui,</hi> but <hi>magna vivere.</hi> Live as becomes the Goſpel which you Preach to others. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Operum copia egregia eſt fandi copia, praeturbeat aliis exemplum, &amp; ſit ejus quaſi copia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi forma vivendi.</hi> He Preacheth beſt who lives beſt, and exemplifies his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in his Life, and Preaches that as profitably in his Converſation, as in the Pulpit. Be a daily Preacher, having your Life a ſtanding Reproof of ſin, and an Argument of Piety, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.19. We well approve of what you have told, us that your ends in the Miniſtry are, to exalt the Glorious Name of your God in the Converſion, Edification, and Salvation of Souls; that you ſeek not your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples goods, but good; not your own profit, but the profit of many, that they might be ſaved; and we hope, pray for, and ſhall rejoyce in your ſucceſs: Let the Lord pour out a double portion of his Spirit upon you, and by his Bleſſing ſo proſper your Studies, that you may be an able Miniſter of the New Teſtament; not of the fleſh, but of the ſpirit; a Workman that needs not to be aſham'd, rightly dividing the word of Truth. Yet if in the diſcharge of your duty, your Labour ſhould be unfruitful, Mourn in ſecret for it, water the Word with your Tears. So did Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41. And <hi>Peter</hi> wept himſelf before he converted others. Pray much for ſucceſs, the Praying Miniſters, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is more ſucceſsful than the Eloquent Orator. Reform your ſelf, perhaps your ſin may hinder the efficacy of the Word, the Seed may not proſper, becauſe ſown with a Leprous hand, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. By no means give over, you are not exempted from yours, becauſe the People neglect their duty. Be not diſcourag'd, your word may thrive afterwards, you are not to limit God, but do your duty. Better be unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful then diſobedient. The Husbandman doth not Sow and Reap in a day. God, even your God will however accept the ſincerity of your obedience and endeavour the will for the deed; and tho' you may ſeem to labour in vain as to the efficacy, yet you ſhall not, as to the reward of your Miniſtry; which is ſecured by him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172319:15"/>who rewards not only Succeſs, but Faithfulneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4, 5. If you have Succeſs, ſet the Grown of Glory on God's Head alone: Know you are but the Inſtrument, He is the principal Agent; you are but the Pipe, He is the Spring whence the Water of Life flows: You do but Sow the Seed, God gives the Succeſs: <hi>Rebecca</hi> Cooks the Meat, but <hi>Iſaac</hi> gives the Bleſſing: <hi>Moſes</hi> hews the Tables, but God writes the Law: Man carries the Bottle, but God gives the Wine: Man may ſpeak words, but God gives Grace. <hi>In coelo Cathedram habet, qui corda movet. Si non ſit intus qui docet, inanis ſtrepitus noſter. Veſtrum eſt docere &amp; dare operam Dei flectare &amp; dare operationem. Paul</hi> can but Plant, <hi>Apollos</hi> Waters, it is God that gives the Increaſe.</p>
               <p>In a word, take heed to your ſelf, to your Doctrine, to your Life. Be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in all things, endure Affliction, make full proof of your Miniſtry, do the Work of a Faithful Paſtor; and the God of all Grace fill you with the Fruits of his Spirit, that you may feed this People with Knowledge and Underſtanding, this Flock, of which you have taken the over-ſight or Epiſcopacy. So ſhall you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from the chief Sheepherd, when he comes to Judgment, a full Reward, even a never-fading Crown of Glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, &amp;c. I cloſe, with that ſtrict Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and earneſt Adjunction of the Great Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>I charge thee, before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall Judge the Quick and the Dead at his appearing, and his Kingdom: Preach the Word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon: Reprove, rebuke, exhort with all Long-ſuffering and Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="address_to_the_people">
               <head>Exhortation to the People.</head>
               <p>HAving told your Miniſter his Duty, perhaps you may ſay, What is this to you: Therefore to make you amends, I ſhall addreſs my ſelf to you, who by holding up your Hands, have declared your Conſent and Willingneſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and acknowledge this our Brother, whom we have ordained, as a Miniſter of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As he is to Preach, you are to Hear; his Preaching and your Hearing are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives; there is a Neceſſity on him to Preach, and on you to Hear; Chriſt hath ordained him by us to Preach, and we in Chriſt's Name command you to Hear. Therefore in the Name and Fear of God, I exhort you to attend on this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God as ſuch, not as an Ordinance of Man; but an Ordinance of God: Go to the Word, as the Word, and for the Word, ſo you may comfortably aſſure your ſelves of God's Bleſſing. God hath given Preaching and Hearing a ſpecial Efficacy, as the ordinary means of Knowledge, Grace and Salvation; come then to the Word as a means of Salvation, be throughly convinced that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172319:16"/>your Salvation is concerned in the Word; think with your ſelves, every Sermon you come to near, that you come to further your Salvation, that your Souls are concerned in this Ordinance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</p>
               <p>Your Miniſter is confined to one Subject, Chriſt, and the Goſpel of Chriſt; he muſt not know any thing elſe among you, and you are not to deſire to know or hear any thing elſe from him.</p>
               <p>He is to give attendance to Reading, to Exhortation, to Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. and you are to be very attentive to hear him, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. <hi>ult. Acts</hi> 8.6. To lay aſide not only Worldly Imployments, but Earthly Deſires; yea roving Thoughts, gating Eyes, and unfixed Ears.</p>
               <p>He is to propound right ends in his Preaching, and you alſo to your ſelves in your Hearing, even thoſe Ends for which God hath appointed his Word to be Preached, as the Inlightning, Convincing, Quickning, Strengthning and Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Souls. Come habitually and actually prepared and diſpoſed, with Prayer and Meditation, conſidering into whoſe Preſence and Service you come; put off your Carnal Affections, purge out your Sins and Corruptions, and compoſe your outward Man to a decent Becomingneſs, and holy Reverence; when you Pray, Sing, or hear. Come in Faith to the Word, with an hiſtorical Faith, believing the Word of God, to be the Word of God, and cloſing with the Truth of it in your Aſſent and Judgment, with a particular applying Faith: Have I an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in this Promiſe? Doth this Threatning belong to me? Doth my Aſſent incline me to Practiſe? Your Miniſter is to Pray in Private and Secret for you, and ſo are you for him: He, for your Spiritual Advantage, as <hi>Paul</hi> bowed his Knees to God for his <hi>Epheſians, Eph.</hi> 3.14. He is to be your Solicitor at the Throne of Grace, before an Orator in the Pulpit, and firſt to breath the Longings of his Soul in Prayer to God, before he vents the Meditations of it to you. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.28. You are to Pray for him, to beg a Door of utterance for him; which Prayer is a Key to open, and reveal the Secret Cabinet of God's Will and Word: Knock then by Prayer at the Gate of Heaven, that God would open his Mouth, both for inward Gifts and Abilities, and the outward Expreſſion of them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18, 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2, 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11. Beg a Door of entrance for your ſelves, that God would open your Hearts; and not only give you an Eye to ſee, but an Heart to embrace the Word, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45. Pray that the Word may have a free paſſage in his Mouth and your Hearts, God muſt do both, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. The Meſſages that he brings, and the Bleſſing of his Labours, is from God; Pray for his Protection, Aſſiſtance, and Succeſs in his Work, which is of great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, very hazardous to miſcarry in, and moſt oppoſed by Earth and Hell: He that is engag'd in this Work, is ſubject to the like Infirmities with his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; yea, he is at work for you; for the Service of your Faith, and your Profit by him, is not a little furthered by your Prayers for him: Forget not then to commend your Miniſter to God. He hath Authority to reprove Sin in any of you, and that plainly and boldly, as one having Authority, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.17.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172319:16"/>It is your Duty to admit and accept of this part of God's Ordinance, even of the word of Reproof, as well as of Inſtruction and Comfort, <hi>James</hi> 1.21. And if you have Grace, you'll take well, and love him the better, that deals Faithfully with you this way, for ſurely much of Grace is ſeen in giving a Reproof duly, and in taking a Reproof thankfully.</p>
               <p>He is to be exemplary in Piety, yet you are not to expect he ſhould be free from ſome Frailties, Weakneſſes and Infirmities, tho' he may from Enormities. He is ſubject to like Paſſions with other Men, ſo was <hi>Elias, Paul,</hi> &amp;c. The High Prieſt himſelf, who was only to enter into the Holy of Holies, was firſt to offer for his own, then for the Sins of the People. Dirt may, but Duſt can hardly be kept from Cloaths. The moſt Godly Miniſter hath his Pillar of Cloud, as well as of Fire. Is he a Man of God? yet but a Man; yea, none are ſo clean, but others may caſt Dirt upon them. Cloaths bruſh'd and clean, may be daſh'd and ſpotted in dirty Ways by paſſers by. Some paint Angels black, becauſe they cannot make them ſo; this was done to Chriſt and the Primitive Chriſtians. Thus it fared with <hi>Athanaſius, Luther, Calvin, Beza,</hi> not to inſtance in the more Modern. And alas! hereby the Power of the Miniſtry is hindred in the Hearts of the Hearers. Look not for Angelical Perfection in your Miniſter, nor Cenſure or Deſpiſe him for the leaſt Infirmity you diſcern in him, or any that are or may be near to him; yea, be loth and unwilling to ſee Infirmities in him, but rather ſet your Eyes on God's Ordinance, and the good things that are in him, and that you receive by him; and make account that he is a Man as well as you, ſubject to the ſame Infirmities that you are.</p>
               <p>He is not to ſhew himſelf Stately, Auſtere, Churliſh, or Strange to any of you, that ſhall be willing to make uſe of him about your Doubts, but to encourage you to move your Doubts to him: You are not careleſly to paſs over what you hear and underſtand not, but to ſeek to know the meaning of it, and to be reſolved, by conferring among your ſelves; and if you that way receive not Satisfaction, you are to go to your Miniſter, your Teacher; and if that will not ferve, go to Chriſt by Prayer. You are to put your Miniſter forward in his Work and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and with Love, Wiſdom and due Reſpect to his Place and Calling, put him in mind of his Duty. Say to <hi>Archippus</hi> is <hi>Faul</hi>'s Charge to the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi> But withal you are to encourage him, not only verbally, but really, allowing him a Competent and Comfortable Maintenance, honouring and reſpecting his Place and Calling; whatever his Perſon deſerves, his Calling is honourable and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges reſpect. You, Sir, are to uſe all good means to gain and maintain the Credit, Reverence, and Eſtimation of your Perſon and Miniſtry in the Hearts of your People; and you, Sirs, are to honour your Miniſter for his Gifts and Works ſake, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. I do not call for the Honour due to the Magiſtrate, and Great Ones of the World; but in your Minds and Judgments you are rightly to eſteem of the need you have of God's Ordinance in his Miniſtry, and of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Benefit you receive by it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. In your Affections and Hearts
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172319:17"/>you are to Reverence him; and in your Practice to yield Obedience to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and be directed by him according to the Word of God. Your Miniſter will thankfully reſent your Civility, when you ſhew Reſpect to his Perſon. Yet I am to let you know, that this is not all that he looks for, or can be contented with, but you would glad his very Heart with the Joyful News of your Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Acceptation of Jeſus Chriſt. May you accept his Labours, may your Perſons, Ears, Hearts, Lives, entertain the Work of his Miniſtry, no Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like this.</p>
               <p>To conclude, Do you, Sir, your utmoſt Endeavour to purſue the Deſign of your Office, and the Ends of year Miniſterial Gifts and Abilities; as an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador to Negotiate this Peoples Reconciliation to God; as an Angel, to be a Miniſtring Spirit ſent forth to Miniſter for them that ſhall be Heirs; as a Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to edifie this People in Faith and Knowledge; as a Steward, to diſtribute what you are intruſted with for the Good of God's Family, the Houſhold of Faith; as a Nurſe, to give out the Sincere Milk of the Word, whereby the Children of God may grow; as a Star, to ſhine for the Benefit of others, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this Night of Ignorance and Atheiſm: This will be your Comfort both here and hereafter, on a Death-bed when your Conſcience ſhall teſtifie to the Sincerity of your Deſires of Saving Souls, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 7. and your Reward will be certain and great, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. you ſhall have a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's Reward, one of thoſe three <hi>Aureola's</hi> mention'd by the <hi>School-men,</hi> an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Acceſſion to the eſſential Happineſs of the Saints.</p>
               <p>O ye People, Do you grow and thrive in Grace, let your Miniſter find the Work of the Lord to proſper in his hands, and ſee his Labour, which is not in vain in the Lord, not to be in vain in your Hearts and Lives: This will be a Credit to the Goſpel, and proclaim to the World that it is more than a meer Notion, and that there is Power, Virtue and Efficacy in it: This will be the Joy of Angels, the Advantage and Comfort of your Paſtor and Miniſter in Life, and at Death; at once a Credit to the Embaſſador and his Meſſage, the Preacher and his Goſpel; and be a Teſtimony and Evidence of the Power of his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: This would ſecure and encourage the Increaſe of his Gifts, when he ſees ſo happy an Iſſue of his Prayers and Sermons, of his many reſtleſs Nights, and weary Days. In a word, This would ſweeten all his Enjoyments, and be your own Concernment and Intereſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
